chapter 13
[Music]
This is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in the public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay hall
The Wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum Chapter fourteen The Winged Monkeys
You will remember that there was no road— —not even a pathway— —between the castle of
the Wicked Witch in the Emerald City.
When the four travelers went in search of the Witch she had seen them coming,
and so sent the Winged Monkeys to bring them to her. It was much harder to find
their way back through the big fields of buttercups and yellow daisies that it
was being carried. They knew, of course, they must go straight east towards the
rising sun; and they started off in the right way. But at noon, when the sun was
over their heads, they did not know which was east and which was west, and that was
the reason they were lost in the great field They kept on walking, however, and
at night the moon came out and shone brightly. So they lay down among the
sweet-smelling yellow flowers and slept soundly until morning— —all but the
Scarecrow and the Tin Woodman. The next morning the sun was behind a cloud, but
they started on, as if they were quite sure which way they were going. “If we
walk far enough,” said Dorothy, “I am sure we shall some time come to some place.”
But day by day passed away, and they still saw nothing before them but the
scarlet field The Scarecrow began to grumble a bit.
“We have surely lost our way,” he said, “and unless we find it again in time to reach
the Emerald City, I shall never get my brains.” “Nor I a heart,” declared the Tin
Woodman. “It seems to me that I can scarcely wait till I get to Oz, and you
must admit that this is a very long journey.” “You see,” said the Cowardly Lion,
with a whimper, “I haven’t the courage to keep tramping forever, without getting
anywhere at all.” Then Dorothy lost heart.
She sat down on the grass and looked at her companions, and they sat down and
looked at her, and Toto found that for the first time in his life he was too
tired to chase a butterfly that flew asked his head. So he put out his tongue
and panted and looked at Dorothy as if to ask what they should do next. “Suppose
we call the field mice,” she suggested.
“They could probably tell us the way to the Emerald City.” “To be sure they could,”
cried the Scarecrow. “Why didn’t we think of that before?”
Dorothy blew the little whistle that she had always carried about her neck since
the Queen of the Mice had given it to her. In a few minutes they heard the
pattering of tiny feet, and many of the small gray mice came running up to her.
Among them was the Queen herself, who asked, in a squeaky little voice: “What can
I do for my friends?” “We have lost our way,” said Dorothy. “Can you tell us where the
Emerald City is?” “Certainly,” answered the Queen; “but it is a great way off, for you
have had it at your backs all this time.” Then she noticed Dorothy’s Golden Cap,
and said, “Why don’t you use the charm of the Cap, and call the Winged Monkeys to
you? They will carry you to the City of
Oz in less than an hour.” “I didn’t know there was a charm,” answered Dorothy, in
surprise. “What is it?” “It is written inside the Golden Cap,” replied the Queen of the
Mice. “But if you are going to call the Winged Monkeys we must run away, for they
are full of mischief and think it great fun to plague us.” “Won’t they hurt me?”
asked the girl anxiously. “Oh, no. They must obey the wearer of the Cap goodbye And
she scampered out of sight, with all the mice hurrying after her. Dorothy looked
inside the Golden Cup and saw some words written upon the lining. These, she
thought, must be the charm, so she read the directions carefully and
put the Cap on pon her head eppie peppy cocky she said, standing on her left foot.
“What did you say?” asked the Scarecrow, who do not know what she was doing hello
hello hello Dorothy went on, standing this time on her right foot. “Hello!”
replied the Tin Woodman calmly Xizhi zusie zyk and said Dorothy, who was now
standing on both feet. This ended the saying of the charm, and they heard a
great chattering and flapping of wings, as the band of Winged Monkeys flew up to them. The
bowed low before Dorothy, and asked, “What is your command?” “We wish to go to the
Emerald City,” said the child, “and we have lost our way.” “We will carry you,” replied
the King, and no sooner than he had spoken than two of the Monkeys caught
Dorothy in their arms and flew away with her. Others took the Scarecrow and the
Woodman and the Lion, and one little Monkey seized Toto and flew after them,
although the dog tried hard to bite him.
The Scarecrow and the Tin Woodman were rather frightened at first, for they
remembered how badly the Winged Monkeys had treated them before; but they saw
that no harm was intended, so they rode through the air quite cheerfully, and had
a fine time looking at the pretty gardens and woods far below them. Dorothy
found herself riding easily between two of the hibiki's one of them the King
himself. They had made a chair of their hands and were careful not to hurt her.
“Why do you have to obey the charm of the Golden Cap?” she asked. “That is a long
story,” answered the King, with a winged laugh; “but as we have a long journey
before us, I will pass the time by telling you about it, if you wish.” “I shall
be glad to hear it,” she replied. “Once,” began the leader, “we
were a free people, living happily in the great forests flying from tree to tree,
eating nuts and fruit, and doing just as we pleased without calling anybody
master. Perhaps some of us were rather too full of mischief at times, flying
down to pull the tails of the animals that had no wings, chasing birds, and
throwing nuts at the people who walked in the forest. But we were careless and
happy and full of fun, and enjoyed every minute of the day. This was many years
ago, long before Oz came out of the clouds to rule over this land. “There
lived here then, away at the North, a beautiful princess, who was also a
powerful sorceress. All her magic was used to help the people, and she was
never known to hurt anyone who was good.
Her name was gala yet and she lived in a handsome palace built from great blocks
of ruby. Everyone loved her, but her greatest sorrow was that she could find
no one to love in return, since all the men were
much too stupid and ugly to mate with one so beautiful and wise. At last,
however, she found a boy who was handsome and manly and wise beyond his years
gala yet made up her mind that when he
grew to be a man she would make him her husband, so she took him to her ruby
palace and used all her magic powers to make him as strong and good and lovely
as any woman could wish. When he grew to manhood
kilala as he was called, was said to be the best and wisest man in all the land,
while his manly beauty was so great that gala yet loved him dearly,
and hastened to make everything ready for the wedding. “My grandfather was at
the time the King of the Winged Monkeys which lived in the forest near gala
let's palace, and the old fellow loved a joke better than a good dinner. One day,
just before the wedding, my grandfather was flying out with his
band when he saw kilala walking beside the river. He was dressed in a rich
costume of pink silk and purple velvet, and my grandfather thought he would see
what he could do. At his word the band flew down and seized cue Lala carrying
him in their arms until they were over the middle of the river, and then dropped
him into the water. “‘Swim out, my fine fellow,’ cried my grandfather, ‘and see if
the water has spotted your clothes Hugh Lala was much too wise not to swim, and
he was not in the least spoiled by all his good fortune. He laughed, when he came
to the top of the water, and swam to the shore. But when gate Lillet came running
out to see him she found his silks and velvet all ruined by the river.
“The princess was angry, and she knew, of course, who did it. She had all the Winged
Monkeys brought before her, and she said at first that their wings should be tied
and they should be treated as they had treated cue Lala and dropped in the
river. But my grandfather pleaded hard, for he knew the Monkeys would drown in
the river with their wings tied, and kilala said a kind word for them also; so that
Galya let finally spared them, on condition that the Winged monkey should
ever after do three times the bidding of the owner of the Golden Cap. This Cap had
been made for a wedding present to cool ala and it was said to have cost the
princess half her Of course my grandfather and all the other Monkeys at once agreed to the
condition, and that is how it happens that we are three times the slaves of
the owner of the Golden Cap whoever it may be.” “And what became of them?” asked
Dorothy, who had been greatly interested in the story Hugh Lala being the first
owner of the Golden Cap,” replied the Monkey, “he was the first to lay his
wishes upon us. As his bride could not bear the sight of us, he called us all to
him in the forest after he had married her and ordered us always to keep where
she could never again set eyes on a Winged Monkey, which we were glad to do,
for we were all afraid of her. “This was all we ever had to do until the Golden
Cap fell into the hands of the Wicked Witch of the West, who made us enslave
the Winkies, and afterward dr.Oz himself out of the Land of the West. Now the
Golden Cap is yours, and three times you have the right to lay your wishes upon
us.” As the Monkey King finished his story Dorothy looked down and saw the green,
shining walls of the Emerald City before them. She wondered at the rapid flight of
the Monkeys, but was glad the journey was over. The strange creatures set the
travelers down carefully before the gate of the City, the King bowed low to
Dorothy, and then flew away swiftly followed by all his band. “That was a good ride,”
said the little girl. “Yes, and a quick way out of our troubles,” replied the Lion. “How
lucky it was you brought away that wonderful Cap end of Chapter 14